and we start at the very top, two lines from the top,
the משנה. mishna. So let's take a look. ואלו טרפות בעוף. v'eilu
tereifos ba'of. So we have done now the list of טרפות tereifos
for large animals, cows also including sheep and goats, which was a
many, many page דף daf in the גמרא, gemara, a few דפים
dapim on a list which is these are the non-טרפות, tereifos, and
now we are on to poultry. So the following are טרפות tereifos
with birds: ניקובת הושט, nikuvat haveshet, so you'll see the list in
some ways is very similar to that of the large animals with
a few variations. So a hole in the esophagus, ופסקת הגרגרת, u'phuskat
hagargeres, a split trachea, which we know means 50 percent. הכתה
חולדה על ראשה, hiksa chuldah al rosha, if a weasel hit it
on its head, מקום שעושה אותה טרפה, makom she'oseh osah tereifah, but
only if it is the place where based on that it would
become a טרפה, tereifah, meaning that the actual hitting on the head
is not enough, as we know from from whatever from the large
animals, it only becomes a טרפה tereifah if it is if it
makes a hole in the what do you call it if it
makes a hole in the membrane. So here too, just hitting it
on the head would not be enough; it would have to be
a hitting on the head which could have caused a hole to
be in the membrane. It is interesting that when it came to
the cows, it says specifically there's a hole in the membrane of
the brain. Here it gives a very graphic example about how that
could occur because you're dealing, it is harder to understand how you
get a hole in the membrane of a brain of a cow,
but here we are dealing with chickens and poultry, so a cat
attacks it, and this is something that could happen. Okay, so now
it goes on.
By the way, רש"י Rashi points out that the הכתה hiksa here,
although hit it sounds like exactly the phrase we would use for
with a hand or with a claw, we know before דרוסה derusah
is the phrase that the גמרא gemara uses for being clawed at,
and רש"י Rashi says here specifically it's not a דרוסה derusah problem,
so it really means using it, hit, attacked by the teeth of
a weasel. So that's interesting. הכתה hiksa literally means to smite, but
that's the way the weasels attack, really
with their teeth.
Yeah, they attack.
Okay, so there you go. So this means that it's specifically the
weasel attacks with its teeth the head of the chicken or whatever
the poultry is, and
חולדה, chuldah, I'm sorry, I kept on saying cat. חולדה, chuldah, right,
right, weasel. Weasel, my mistake, my mistake, right, okay, weasel. So it
was being attacked by a weasel,
and again, by its teeth, which makes it not a case of
דרוסה, derusah, and it's just a more graphic or concrete example of
the problem of a hole in the membrane, of a קרום של
מוח, krum shel moach, but here it says that if it was
again bit in a place where it could have made that hole,
we are concerned with that hole. Okay, ניקב הקורקבן, nikav hakorkovan, so
now the קורקבן, korkovan, which is the gizzard, and we must have
a nice picture of that somewhere here.
Just one of the Artscrolls. Oh, there is.
Basically, as the neck goes down there from the thing, you've got
a before it hits the stomach. Now chickens don't have and birds
don't have the four stomachs of a cow, right, because they are
not ruminants, and they don't chew their cud, okay, but they do
have some type of a thing called the crop and the gizzard,
which sort of chops up their food before it gets to their
stomach. I can't find where this is. You want to show your
picture there, Artscroll
on the 56a?
Let me see here. Okay, oh, here we go.
I'm sorry, זפק zefek is the crop, קורקבן korkovan is the gizzard.
Okay, and it first goes, here's a very lovely picture with a
chicken head bent back so you see where it starts and where
it ends. You know, these obviously are the small intestines, okay, so
anyway, so this is the it goes here, goes first into the
crop and then into the gizzard. Okay, so the זפק zefek is
the crop, the קורקבן korkovan is the gizzard. So the קורקבן korkovan
comes second. All right, so that's that's the way the that's what
a chicken looks like. All right, so if it has a hole,
ניקב הקורקבן, nikav hakorkovan, so again, which we say that was the
gizzard, okay, so the gizzard has a hole in it,
ניקבו הדקין, nikvu hadakin, the small intestines have a hole in it,
נפלו לאור ונחמרו בני מעיה, naflu la'ur venichmeru bnei mei'eha, if it
fell into fire and the and the inner organs became like shriveled,
you know, instead not burnt but shriveled by the fire. אם ירוקים
פסולים, im yerukim psulim, now if they became shriveled and they're green,
that's no good. אם אדומים כשרים, im adumim ksheirim, if they're red,
presumably they started red and they remained red, we'll see about that
in the גמרא, gemara, כשרה, kshera, it's kosher.
דרסה, darsa, now we're back to, so that's a much shorter list,
I should say, than the cows. Okay, the cows have a lot
of stomachs and various things. Anyway, we'll see in the גמרא gemara
that basically we assume the lists are the same except for where
they're either mentioned different or where the anatomy is different. Okay, דרסה
וטרפה בכותל, darsa v'tarfa bakosel, if some other animal or person trampled
on it, רש"י Rashi says it means a person accidentally trampled on
it, or smacked it against the wall. Interesting the word טרפה tarfa
here, which is, you know, not literally mean טרפה, tereifah, which means
like clawed at, but anyway here... means like thrown against the wall,
so this is like the case of ריסוק איברים. Risuk Evarim. You
remember the case in the משנה Mishna about the cat that fell
off the roof? So here the תרתי tartei imagine how a chicken
gets its sort of limbs not shattered, but there was this like
blunt impact which could have caused this loosening of limbs. So the
example it gives is not falling off of a roof, but getting
trampled. או שרצצה בהמה, O she-retzatza behema, or an animal sort of
crushed it or stomped on it,
ומפרכסת, u-mefarkeset, and it’s so it’s still thrashing around.
So what is the story? ושהתה מעת לעת ושחטה, Ve-shahata me-et le-et
ve-shachata, if it waited 24 hours and you slaughtered it, כשרה, keshera,
it’s kosher. So again, you remember when the משנה Mishna talked about
a בהמה behema falling off the roof, it did not mention the
24 hours. The גמרא Gemara borrowed the concept of 24 hours from
this משנה Mishna and said that if basically there’s like this blunt
impact, so you have if it doesn't move for 24 hours it’s
a טרפה treifa even if there’s no problems with the internal organs.
If it does wait for 24 hours or it stood up, then
you slaughter it you’re okay, but you still have to check the
internal organs. Only if it walked around,
then you do not have to worry about checking the internal organs.
So this is the problem of ריסוק איברים. Risuk Evarim. So it
is very way similar, it’s not as complete of a list. It
has some more specific, like I said, like very graphic examples, talking
about let’s say being attacked by a weasel and it does of
course mention the issue about the קורקבן, korkevan, about the gizzard. So
let’s take a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara. רב ושמואל ולוי דאמרי, Rav u-Shmuel ve-Levi de-amri, רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel and לוי Levi all say, what do you do
if this chicken has been attacked
by
a weasel and there’s a hole in the skull and you want
to see if the hole went down into the membrane of the
brain? Now presumably, the reason the משנה Mishna described it like this
and the reason that we’re going to find here that it’s like
we didn’t have a similar discussion by cows, is presumably by cows
it’s easier to inspect. First of all, you crack open the hole,
you have more to deal with, you crack open the skull, you
can look at the brain, it’s not so tiny. And number two,
it seems that the weasel, if it made a hole, would have
made a very thin hole, so it would be hard to identify.
So here the question is: you saw that it was attacked in
the skull, if it went all the way in and made a
hole in the membrane, you’ve got a problem. How do you determine
that? So let’s take a look. רב ושמואל ולוי דאמרי, Rav u-Shmuel
ve-Levi de-amri, they all say: מכניס ידו לבפנים, machnis yado lifnim, you
stick your hand inside like the basically the mouth of the chicken
or the skull from underneath you get into the skull, ובודק, u-vodek,
and you check with your finger. אם מבצבץ המוח טרפה ואם לאו
כשרה. Im me-vatz-betz ha-mo'ach treifa ve-im lav keshera. Basically what you do
is you push the brain up to the top of the skull.
So there’s a hole. You saw that it was attacked here by
this weasel and there’s a hole in the skull. The question is:
did it get down into the membrane? So from below you push
the brain up. If brain matter comes up through that hole, okay,
then you know that the hole goes all the way down through
the membrane. If no brain matter is coming up, then you know
the membrane is still intact and even though you’re applying pressure, nothing
is getting up through the hole. Okay, so that’s how you check
to see if the hole went all the way through. No no,
after you slaughtered it.
Oh, you slaughtered it. You slaughtered it, so the animal didn’t kill
it.
Right, the animal attacked the skull, now you want to know: did
the teeth of the weasel get into the membrane around the brain?
So you push the brain up, if brain matter comes up through
the hole in the skull, then you know the membrane has been
pierced as well. If no brain matter comes up, then you know
it has not. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: הניחא למאן דאמר
עד דמנקיב קרומא תתאה. Ha nicha le-man de-amar ad de-mankiv kruma tata'ah.
That’s good if it’s a טרפה treifa only until the inner membrane
gets cut. Basically there’s a membrane that’s more on the inside of
the skull and that’s the outer membrane, and then there’s a membrane,
a very thin membrane that’s around the brain itself, the inner membrane.
So if you say it’s only a problem if the hole goes
through both membranes, then it’s a good test because then if nothing
is coming through, that means that there’s no hole. But אלא למאן
דאמר ניקב עילאה
אף על גב דלא ניקב תתאה, ela le-man de-amar nikav ila'ah af
al gav de-lo nikav tata'ah, if it’s enough for the upper membrane
to have a hole even without the lower one, so what type
of a test is it? Right? ניחוש, neichosh, let’s be concerned, דילמא
עילאה ניקב ותתאה לא ניקב, dilma ila'ah nikav ve-tata'ah lo nikav, let’s
be concerned that the outer membrane, the one closest around the skull
in the inside of the skull has a hole, which would make
it a טרפה, treifa, the inner membrane does not have a hole,
so nothing will come up through the hole because the inner membrane
is still intact, but the animal is still a טרפה. treifa. So
the גמרא Gemara says: No, אי איתא דניקב עילאה, ee ita de-nikav
ila'ah, if it was true that the upper one had a hole,
תתאה אגב רוחיה מיפסק פסק. tata'ah agav ruchya mifsek pasak. You’re changing
the conditions when you’re doing this experiment, you’re applying pressure and pushing
something against the skull. So if all that had to protect it
was the inner membrane, then as you were pushing, okay, the inner
membrane would tear and it would come up through it. So therefore
yes, if you push and nothing comes up, it means the outer
membrane does not have a hole because if as long as the
outer membrane had a hole, then even if the inner one did
not and you pushed, it would still create, it would still tear
and it would come
up, so. Right, so that's great. So if it's enough for the
outer one to have a hole, you say, well don't worry, this
test will get it out even if just the outer one has
a hole. Fine, but if you need the inner one to have
a hole, then all this test proves is that the outer one
has the hole. It doesn't prove that it goes all the way
through, right? So you still can have a false positive. Now, of
course, at least you're playing it safe, at least it's לחומרא l'chumra
you'll think it's a טריפה treifa when it's not. And maybe there's
no other way to do it, but at least now you don't
have a perfect test. Because according to the גמרא, Gemara, all it
really proves is that the outer one had a hole. Now, the
inner one might have broke as a result of your applying pressure.
Yes, Charlie.
Is an egg from a טריפה treifa animal also
טריפה? treifa?
Yes. And actually, if an animal is a ספק טריפה, safek treifa,
also milk. If an animal is a ספק טריפה safek treifa or
a ודאי טריפה, vadai treifa, then you cannot have the eggs or
the milk. If you שחט shacht an animal and find that it's
a טריפה, treifa, you can assume that this goes back to חזקה
chazaka purposes, you can assume maybe some of it a little unrealistically
that the problem occurred like only within the last day and all
the milk and the eggs prior are not a problem unless you
have specific reason to know otherwise. But as soon as there's a
ספק, safek, you're right, you can no longer be, you know, once
it's at, you know, once you have to consider it a ספק,
safek, meaning not that it's just, sometimes it's a doubt that you
have to do a test, but if you can't test, you'll assume
it's okay. But if it's at the level where it's a doubt
where you cannot make any assumption even בדיעבד, b'diavad, then yes, you
can't eat the milk or the egg. There's actually a problem that
occurred every now and then, every few years there's always a new
problem coming up with eggs, with milk, because they inject growth hormones
into cows, and the growth hormones and the needle, there's a serious
concern makes a hole in one of the inner organs and makes
it a טריפה. treifa. So, you know, is that enough to create,
make all of the milk ספק טריפה safek treifa and therefore you
cannot drink any milk? So obviously not, because we're still drinking milk,
but it always becomes an issue every time, you know, every few
years these types of questions come up again. What did you want
to say, Charlie?
Is it the טריפות treifos that we were talking about for birds,
do we routinely check for those?
No. The only thing we routinely check for is the lungs of
a cow.
The lungs are missing from this list.
Right, that's true. Yeah, this list is not a complete list. But
yeah, these things we really do not routinely check for. Okay, the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, so אמר זעירי. Amar Zeiri. So now we
know how to check if there's a hole in the skull that
you do a test to determine if brain matter comes out, then
you know that at least there's a hole in the outer membrane
and if none does, you're safe. אמר זעירי, Amar Zeiri, אין בדיקה
לחולדה. ein bdika l'chulda.
You cannot check for this weasel and therefore once it's, once it
attacked the skull, made a hole in the skull, you've, you just
have to be מחמיר. machmir. You have to play it safe and
say it's no good. How come you can't check? So מפני ששיניה
דקות, mipnei sheshineha dakot,
because it has very thin teeth. Now, that's why you can't do
a visual inspection, but why not do this inspection we just mentioned?
So the גמרא Gemara says וכי שיניה דקות מאי הוי, vechi shineha
dakot mai havay, who cares it has thin teeth? Or you know,
we just gave you a way to do a test that would
regardless of whether you can see it or not. So אמר רב
אושעיא Amar Rav Oshaya מפני ששיניה דקות ועקומות, mipnei sheshineha dakot ve'akumot,
its teeth are thin and they are angled, they are bent. So
the concern here is that where there's the hole in the skull
is, the hole underneath in the membrane of the brain is not
directly under it, right? So if you've got an angled hole, a
diagonal, a diagonal attack, right, so unless you push up exactly at
that angle, which you're not always able to do, it's not going
to prove anything. This will prove only if the hole goes straight
down. So he says this test won't work. Okay, the hole in
the skull does not necessarily correspond to where the hole in the
membrane exists.
So כי סליק לנהרדעא, ki salik l'Nahardea, so this is what זעירי
Zeiri said originally. When he went to נהרדעא, Nahardea, שלח להו, shalach
lehu, so they,
so he sent to them, to the rabbis he left behind wherever
he came from, I don't know where זעירי Zeiri originally came from,
but anyway, he went to נהרדעא, Nahardea, he learned in the ישיבה
yeshiva there, he learned from different teachers, and then he sent the
following message back to his students from נהרדעא, Nahardea, דברים שאמרתי לפניכם
טעות הם בידי. devarim she'amarti lifneichem ta'ut hem beyadi.
What I told you in the past, it's a mistake. I recant.
Okay, so that's pretty interesting. ברם כך אמרו משמיה דרבי שמעון בן
לקיש, Bram kach amru mishmei de'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, this is what
they say in the name of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, gotta note
the irony here. He's going to נהרדעא Nahardea and he's reporting to
them a teaching of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, who was from ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And especially if you remember the גמרא Gemara earlier,
where they told something to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael in the name of רב, Rav, and he wouldn't even
acknowledge the authority or who רב Rav was. So anyway, here he's
saying now, he went to נהרדעא Nahardea and he's teaching them in
the name of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. This is what they say
in the name of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, בודקים לחולדה ביד אבל
לא במחט. Bodkim l'chulda beyad aval lo bemachat.
You can check for a, for this case of the weasel with
your hand, like we said before, with the pushing underneath from your
hand, but you can't use a nail. Now, why would you want
to use a nail? So apparently if a nail is not to
do the same test, the nail is you run the nail over
the brain itself and you see whether it gets caught on anything.
So, you know, if the tip of it gets caught on something,
then you would be able to identify the hole. So it would
be a test from directly on the membrane, not pushing from below.
Okay, that won't work because we're afraid the nail itself will create
a hole.
Okay, Rabbi Yochanan and Rabbi Elazar says אפילו מסמר, afillu masmer, you
can even use a nail to do this test. So we're not
afraid you'll create a hole. ובפלוגתא, uviphlugeta, this is something that has
been debated before, between
Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Nechemiah. חד בדיק בידא וחד בדיק במחטא, chad
badik beyada vechad badik bemachata,
one used a hand and one used a needle. So מאן דבדיק
בידא אמר ליה למאן דבדיק במחטא, man de'vadik beyada amar leh leman
de'vadik bemachata, so the one who used the hand said to the
one who used the needle, עד מתי אתה מכלה ממונם של ישראל?
ad matai ata mechaleh mamonam shel Yisrael? How long are you going
to be wasting the money of the Jewish people? Because if you're
checking with a needle, your needle is going to half the time
make the hole itself. So you'll want to be safer, you know,
you want to be extra careful to do a test that you
think is better, but your test is going to lead to a
lot of false positives. And therefore, how long are you going to
be wasting the money of the Jewish people? So, you can guess
what the response is going to be: אמר ליה מאן דבדיק במחטא
למאן דבדיק בידא, amar leh man de'vadik bemachata leman de'vadik beyada, so
the one who checked with the needle said to the one who
checked with the hand, עד מתי אתה מאכיל לישראל נבילות? ad matai
ata ma'achil leYisrael nevelot? How long are you going to feed the
Jewish people treif food? Your test is my, you say my test
has too many false positives, your test doesn't have enough of a,
you know, enough accurate positives. Your test has too many false negatives.
So you're, you know, you're going to feed them treif food. So
he actually said נבילות. nevelot. So the Gemara says נבילות? נבילות? והא
שחוטה היא? nevelot? nevelot? veha shechutah hi?
What do you mean nevelot? You slaughtered it. Okay, אלא טריפות. ela
tereifot. All right, he didn't mean that literally. Fine, tereifot. שמא נקב
קרום המוח, shema nikav krum hammoach, because maybe you've got a hole
in the membrane. So here you have a nice beautiful distillation of
what still today plays out, you know, if you would go all
the way back to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
Who are you more afraid you know, are you more afraid that
you're going to be too lenient and that the law will be
compromised, or are you more afraid that you're going to be strict
and it will create an undue and an unfair burden, you know,
on the people? So that could both be a question about what
are the laws you actually make, which is a lot of the
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai debate, right? Are we
going to make a safeguard, don't do this lest you come to
do that to protect the law? Or are we afraid that creates
an undue restriction on human activity and freedom, right? Or it could
also be about how you deal with areas about, you know, applying
the laws and areas of doubt? Right? So how much are you
sort of sensitive to the implications on people's lives and how much
are you being, you know, extra sensitive in terms of perhaps, you
know, perhaps a possible violation? So it's a very nice distillation of
what the type of, you know, tensions that have gone on forever
and still go on today. Yes, Rivka?
When he said you can't examine, was that a קולא kulla or
a
חומרא? chumra?
It seems like it was a חומרא, chumra, because it seems like
it was a חומרא chumra that once we have this attack from
the weasel, we have to concern be, you know, we have to
assume it's a טריפה treifa unless we know otherwise. So now he
was being more lenient, right. Exactly. Exactly. So, right, the dominant approach
here in the Gemara is that you do the test. But again
in the end we said the quest and that you do the
test with the hand, which led to fewer, you know, positives than
doing the test with the nail.
When she said you can't examine, why do we assume
that he was being מחמיר? machmir? Then maybe he was saying just
forget about it, since you can't examine.
Well, because the Mishnah says the Mishnah doesn't even say that the
membrane was pierced. The Mishnah says if it was attacked by a
weasel where it could have made it a טריפה. treifa. So the
simple read of the Mishnah is as soon as it was attacked
and the possibility is there, it's a טריפה. treifa. So the whole
discussion in the Gemara that you can test for it is a
you know, is clearly being more lenient than the simple ruling of
the Mishnah, right? The simple ruling of the Mishnah is once it's
a possibility, it's a טריפה. treifa.
Charlie, you had a comment or no? Okay. All right. So anyway
so there you go. So that was a debate of whether you
do it a more, you know, a test with possible false positives
or possible false negatives. Okay. So now the Gemara says תסתיים, tistayeim,
let us conclude דבדיק בידא רבי יהודה הוא. derabbi Yehuda hu de'vadik
beyada. Rabbi Yehuda was the one who did the test with the
hand, which was the one which led to fewer positives. דתניא: רבי
שמעון אלעזר אומר משום רבי יהודה: detanya: Rabbi Shimon Elazar omer mishum
Rabbi Yehuda: בודקים לחולדה ביד אבל לא במסמר. bodkim lechulda beyad aval
lo bemasmer.
It's pretty clear, you can check you check for this concern about
the attack of a weasel with the hand, but you do not
use a nail. נשבר העצם אף על פי שלא ניקב קרום המוח.
nishbar ha'etzem af al pi shelo nikav krum hammoach. Now this last
line seems bizarre and the Gemara will analyze it, and it's a
problem even if the skull is broken, even if the membrane is
not broken. Well then why are you doing a test? So we'll
get back to that line in a minute. But anyway, so the
Gemara says תסתיים. tistayeim. You're right, that clears that up, it's clearly
Rabbi Yehuda who says you do the test with a hand and
not with a nail. So now the Gemara looks at this last
line though: הגופא קשיא. hagufa kashya. One minute, this is an internal
contradiction. אמרת בודקים לחולדה ביד אבל לא במסמר. amarta bodkim lechulda beyad
aval lo bemasmer. You say you do this test with your hand
but not with the nail. אלמא אית ליה בדיקותא. alma it leh
bedikuta.
So it can be you can run do a test and determine
that everything is okay, even after the... the skull has been pierced.
So והדר תניא, Vehadar tanya, and then the last line of the
of this ברייתא baraita said, נשבר העצם אף על פי שלא ניקב
קרום של מוח, nishbar haetzem af al pi shelo nikav krum shel
moach, that a crack in the skull, a hole in the skull
is in is a טרפה treifah even if the membrane has not
been pierced. So if that's true, what's the whole point of the
test? So אלמא ליכא בדיקותא, Alma leika bedikusah, there's no purpose of
a test. So the גמרא Gemara says, סיפא אתאן לעוף המים. seifa
atan le'of hamayim. The end is going to a water fowl.
So when by water fowl, you don't need to pierce the membrane,
it's enough to just crack, you know, put a hole in the
skull. Why is that? הואיל ואין לו קרום, ho'il ve'ein lo krum,
since it does not have a membrane around its brain. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אין לו קרום סלקא דעתך? ein lo krum salka
daitach? What, you really think that's true, it doesn't have a membrane?
Of course it has a membrane. Pretty amazing like the גמרא Gemara
knows all this stuff just off the top like that. Okay, anyway,
what do you mean, of course it has a membrane, אלא הואיל
וקרומו רך, ela ho'il vekrumo rach,
since it has a very thin or literally soft, but presumably thin
membrane. So therefore even if the membrane is not pierced, as soon
as there's a hole in the skull, we assume eventually it will
pierce the membrane. You could say it one of two ways. You
could say as soon as there's a hole in the skull, the
animal will die even without a pierced membrane, but the way רש״י
Rashi says, which maybe probably makes more sense given the paradigm we're
dealing with is, you can assume that the membrane will tear as
well. So when you're dealing with water fowl, it's enough that there's
a hole in the skull, you don't need the hole in the
membrane, but by the other bird, a hole in the membrane suffice
you need a hole in the membrane and you can do this
test to determine whether it's there. Charlie, you have information for us
about water fowl?
I'm looking up ducks.
You're looking up ducks as to whether they have holes in the
membrane. Okay, what the size of the membrane. You have to look
up ducks, brain, membrane. Okay, tell me what you find. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב
ענאן. Amar lei Rav Nachman leRav Anan. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said to רב ענאן, Rav Anan,
מר אמר שמואל, mar amar Shmuel, the master, you said in the
name of שמואל, Shmuel, בדיק בידיה ומכשיר, badik bideih umachshir, that שמואל
Shmuel would test
with his hand
and if no brains came up by pushing up the brains, you
know, none came through the hole, he would say it's כשר. kosher.
והונא חבריין אמר אמר רב, Vehuna chavrayan amar amar Rav, and
הונא Huna our friend
says רב Rav also would use his hand to check and if
it didn't and if nothing came up, he would say it's כשר.
kosher. והתני לוי, Vahatni Levi, but didn't לוי Levi teach טרפות שמנו
חכמים בבהמה כנגדן בעוף. treifos shemanu chachamim bebeheimah kenegdan ba'of. So by
the way, this is a very important teaching, which we're going to
say again, because our list of טרפות treifos by bird is not
nearly as extensive as the animals. So לוי Levi has a general
principle, the general rule is anything mentioned by animals is true by
birds, unless we say otherwise, and of course, or unless the anatomy
is different like animals, you know, have these multiple stomachs that birds
don't, but anyway, that's the general ruling.
יתר עליהן עוף, yeser aleihen of, the bird has more טרפות treifos
in which case, נשבר העצם אף על פי שלא ניקב קרום של
מוח, nishbar haetzem af al pi shelo nikav krum shel moach, if
there was a hole in the skull even without the membrane being
pierced. And we should admit at this stage that that's the פשט
pshat of our משנה. Mishna. But our משנה Mishna says it was
attacked by a weasel where it could מקום שעושה אותה טרפה, makom
she'oseh osah treifah, in a place where it makes it a טרפה.
treifah. Well, at least our משנה Mishna is somewhat ambiguous, okay, but
our משנה Mishna never spoke about the membrane having a hole. It
sounded like it's enough that the head was attacked, that that's a
problem. So here we have a ברייתא baraita that says actually birds
are stricter than large animals, presumably because they're more delicate, you know,
they're tiny compared to an animal, and therefore a hole in the
skull is enough. So how could you be saying you need to
have a hole in the membrane and you can do this test?
So he said, אמר ליה, Amar lei,
and how did רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel do this test if
so? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, התם בעוף
המים. hasam be'of hamayim.
Same answer. Anywhere you find it saying that you don't need to
be a hole in the membrane, that's about water fowl. הואיל ואין
לו קרום, ho'il ve'ein lo krum, since there's no membrane. אין לו
קרום סלקא דעתך? ein lo krum salka daitach? You really think that
there's no membrane? אלא אימא הואיל וקרומו רך, ela eima ho'il vekrumo
rach, because it has a very thin, delicate membrane and therefore yes,
there are some birds that you don't need a hole in the
membrane, no test will be any good, those are water fowl, but
other birds, it's just like a large animal, it needs a hole
in the membrane and there's a way to test for it. Charlie,
you have some information you want to share? Not finding anything. Not
finding anything. I can't believe there's not more on the internet about
the membranes around the brains of ducks. Okay.
I wonder if this has anything about that. Hold on.
No.
Totally skips it. For some bizarre reason.
Okay, you'll tell us if there's something in the שיחות חולין Sichos
Chullin book, Charlie. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. רב
שיזבי בדיק בשמשא. Rav Shizbi badik beshimsha. Now רב שיזבי, Rav Shizbi,
when he was looking for holes in the membrane, he checked with
with the sun, maybe he held it up to the sun and
saw if it reflected in different ways, it would indicate the hole.
רב יימר בדיק במיא. Rav Yeimar badik bemaya. רב יימר Rav Yeimar
tested with water. What is the test with water? So רש״י Rashi
has two possibilities. One is you pour the water in the skull,
like what, it does have a...
he's holding it up to the sun.
Oh, he's holding it up to the sun. Is there anything there
about the membrane in the skull and waterfowl?
I don't see anything.
Okay, wait.
Did I skip a line?
A few lines. I did? Yeah.
Oh, I'm sorry, I did.
You're right. Where am I? Oh, okay. Thank you very much. I
did, because it's what's called תשמט על ידי הדומות. tashmat al yedei
hadomos. I skipped to... thank you very much, I skipped to where
the exact same line appears later in the same דף. daf. Okay,
let's go back. Thank you.
ההיא תרנגולתא דהויא בי רב חנא. Hahi tarnigolta d'hava bei Rav Chana.
So we're now five lines from the bottom. There was a chicken
in the house of רב חנא, Rav Chana, which apparently was attacked
by a weasel in the head. שדרה לקמיה דרב מתנה. Shadra l'kamia
d'Rav Matna. He sent it in front of רב מתנה. Rav Matna.
נשבר העצם. Nishbar ha'etzem. Now here it tells you what the case
was. The skull had a hole, ולא ניקב קרום של מוח. v'lo
nikav krum shel moach. But there was no hole, or it was
crushed the skull, but there was no hole in the membrane.
ואכשרה. V'achshara. And he said it was kosher. אמר ליה. Amar lei.
He said, והתנן באלו טריפות שמונה חכמים בבהמה כנגדן בעוף. V'hatnan b'eilu
treifot shmona chachamim b'vehema k'negdan b'of. Here you see why I jumped
to the exact same line. Anyway, doesn't לוי Levi say that the
טריפות treifot that the rabbis say by... by large animals is the
same by... by birds? יתר עליהם עוף. Yeter aleihem of. But birds
have even more טריפות. treifot. נשבר העצם אף על פי שלא ניקב
קרום של מוח. Nishbar ha'etzem af al pi shelo nikav krum shel
moach. If there... if there's a hole in the skull even without
it being a hole in the membrane. אמר ליה. Amar lei. התם
בעוף השמים. Hatam b'of hashamayim. That's only about waterfowl. הואיל ואין לו
קרום. Hoil v'ein lo krum. Because it has no... because it
has no, what do you call it, it has no membrane. אין
לו קרום סלקא דעתך? Ein lo krum salka datcha? What, literally? לא,
אלא אימא הואיל וקרום שלו רך. Lo, ela eima hoil v'krum shelo
rach. It has a delicate membrane. Okay, we basically repeated the whole
thing except here with a practical case and dealing with this... with
this chicken that was attacked. Yes.
There is a עוף השמים of hashamayim diagram at the top of
the right.
Does it show how the membrane is thinner? It just points to
something and says thin membrane.
Okay. Why did he ask the question if he was so shocked
by the answer? He assumed it wasn't going to be good, then
why did he send him the chicken?
That's
maybe because he... maybe that's a good question. Maybe because he knew
that there were teachings, you know, maybe he himself felt ambivalent... sort
of conflicted about it. He knew there were rabbis out there that
tested. He had this teaching about that it doesn't matter with the
hole, so he didn't feel like he was in a position to
פסקן. pasken. So once this guy gave the פסק, psak, he articulated
what his... what his ambivalence is, you know. That type of stuff
does happen in the... in real life, you know. You feel, look,
I don't know how to resolve these problems, let me send it
to somebody else. But then, you know, so once he פסקןed, pasken
he said, oh, so okay, so explain this to me.
Okay. רב שיזבי
בדק בשמשא. Rav Shizvi badak b'shimsha. So רב שיזבי Rav Shizvi tested
for these holes in the membrane by the sun. רב יימר בדק
במיא. Rav Yemar badak b'maya. רב יימר Rav Yemar tested with water.
Now what type of test with water? So רש"י Rashi says one
possibility is, hard to imagine how you do this with a tiny
delicate little membrane, diagram. Okay, thank you. One... well, that's only the
second explanation. No, one רש"י Rashi says is you scoop out the
brains from the membrane. It's a very thin membrane around it, I
don't know how you would do it. And then you fill the
membrane sack essentially with water and you see if any water drips
out. So רש"י, Rashi, that's one explanation. רש"י Rashi sort of acknowledges
that it's pretty hard to imagine how you successfully do that. So
רש"י's Rashi other explanation is you pour the water into the skull
through the hole and then you swish it around or whatever, and
then you pour it out. And if it's clear water, so you
know there was no hole in the membrane. If the water has
some type of, you know, cloudy and white matter, it means that
it got through into the brain and took some of the brains
with it, and then you know that it did get through the
membrane. Now, you might remember these phrases, testing with the sun, testing
with the water, from another context, from testing for פגימה pgima on
the knife, right? So he holds it up to the sun, you
run drops of water down it and see if it catches. So
it's very interesting, the exact same language for very different types of
tests.
Okay. רב אחא בר יעקב בדק בגילא דחיטתא. Rav Acha bar Yaakov
badak b'gila d'chitata. He checked with a... type of a... of a
needle of like of... of tailors. So the same type of thing,
this was the stricter test that you ran the nail, the needle
on the tip and you saw if it caught. אמר רב שיזבי.
Amar Rav Shizvi. So רב שיזבי Rav Shizvi says, הני אווזי דידן,
Hani avazi didan, our... I keep on forgetting, is an אווזא avaza
a duck? What's a goose?
I
thought it said goose now. אווזא Avaza is a goose.
ברבזא Barbaza is a... goose?
I thought it translates a goose.
Goose. Okay. So our geese כעוף השמים דמיין, k'of hashamayim damyan, are
like waterfowl. I did not understand this גמרא Gemara when I read
it. Are like waterfowl? So what is a real waterfowl if it's
not a goose?
I know, I don't get it. So, okay, maybe it means our
geese, maybe their geese spent more time on the land. Are there
different types of geese?
Well, that's what רש"י Rashi says, that the geese are
always והא תמיד במיא. v'ha tamid b'maya.
I know, but if they're always in the water, then of course...
then what do you mean they're like waterfowl? Then they are waterfowl.
Meaning, the statement only makes sense if you say these geese are
not so much in the water, but nevertheless they are still considered
waterfowl. But if these geese are always in the water, so what
do you mean
they...
Canadian geese.
Canadian geese
are in the water all the
time, and they're much more comfortable in the water than on land.
They're very odd—they're great swimmers, but they're very awkward on land. Oh,
okay.
So let's go back to the ones in Kennedy Airport.
All right. Oh, I see. So you're saying the opposite. But I'm
still bothered with the word דמיון, dimyon, and דמיון dimyon means that's
in my mind that they're not genuine to that, they're just, you
know, they're just similar to it. Close enough. I don't know. Okay.
So that is the question about whether you need a hole in
the membrane and how to test for it and the difference between
waterfowl and other birds. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. נפלו לאור.
naflu la'or. This is again something that we did not have something
similar in the משנה, Mishnah, presumably by cows, because presumably this type
of stuff doesn't happen to cows. So it fell into the fire,
and then it got burnt on the outside, so you open it
up and if the inner organs have changed to green, then it
is a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב
יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן יהושע: Amar Rav Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yosi
ben Joshua: הירוקתן—the hayerukatan amount of
how much of them have to—how much of the organs have to
turn green? Like, you know, a tiny little green spot? So he
says the amount of green כשיר ניקובתן keshier nikuvatan is the same
amount that a hole would be a problem, which makes sense, right?
Because then you assume that if it's got that size of a
problem, it will, you know, ultimately it will rupture and something will
happen. So מה ניקובתן במשהו, ma nikuvatan b'mashehu, the same way even
the tiniest hole in the inner organs is a problem, אף הירוקתן
במשהו af hayerukatan b'mashehu if they've turned green as a result of
this fire, then that's also a problem. We assume that, you know,
this green spot will ultimately become a rupture and will or have
similar types of problems as a hole. So בעי מיניה רב יוסף
בריה דרב יהושע בן לוי מרבי יהושע בן לוי. ba'ei minei Rav
Yosef bereih d'Rav Yehoshua ben Levi mi-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. So the
son of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi asked Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, הוריקה
כבד כנגד בני מעיים מהו? horika kaved keneged b'nei mei'ayim mahu? The
liver, which as you all remember, if the liver, most of the
liver is removed it's not a problem, so presumably if the liver
turned green it's not a problem, okay, because the liver is less
essential, at least the majority of it. But what if a part
of it turned green opposite the rest of the inner organs? So,
you know, will
that be like there was a hole on the inner organs because
it really is only on the liver?
Okay. So he said, אמר ליה טריפה. amar leh treifah. It's טריפה.
treifah. ולא יהא אלא ניטלה. v'lo yehei ella nitlah. Let it be
no different than if the whole organ had been—I'm sorry, I misread
that. ולא יהא אלא ניטלה. v'lo yehei ella nitlah. So the question
comes back is, but you know, so what? Even if the liver
had been removed it would still be כשר. kosher. Who cares if
it has this greenness?
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, כיון שהוריקה כבד כנגד בני מעיים, kivan
shehorika kaved keneged b'nei mei'ayim, since it's green right where it connects
to the other organs, בידוע שנפלו לאור ונחמרו בני מעיים. beyadua shenafelu
la'or v'nechamru b'nei mei'ayim. We can assume the greenness on the liver
also means that opposite it on the other organs has been similarly
affected. So even though you only see, right, so the liver lays
on top of other organs. So yes, it's true, if the liver
has a hole it's not a problem, if the liver is largely
removed it's not a problem, but if there's a green on the
area where, you know, where the liver is laying—meaning if this, you
know, if this is the liver and this is the other organ
and the green is right here on the underside of the liver
where it's opposite the other organ, so then they say that's evidence.
It's true, if that was just a hole it wouldn't be a
problem, but if it's there that's evidence that the area opposite it
on the other organ also has been affected by the fire and
therefore is also a problem, although you don't see the greenness on
the other organ. Okay. So and therefore ונחמרו בני מעיים, v'nechamru b'nei
mei'ayim, that's evidence that if they did become shriveled, וטריפה v'treifah and
it's טריפה. treifah. Now I do want to point out another thing
other than the question of just the liver and the other organs,
which is, let's say you spot this green spot but you don't
have evidence that it fell into the fire. Is it that you
need—fell into the fire creates the problem, then you search for these
spots and then if you see it, it confirms that it was
a problem and it's טריפה? treifah? That's how the discussion started. The
משנה Mishnah said it fell into the fire and there's greenness. And
then you say, well, where is that greenness, how much and so
on. The last line sounds a little different. The last line says
that בידוע שנפלו לאור ונחמרו בני מעיים. beyadua shenafelu la'or v'nechamru b'nei
mei'ayim. If you see the green spot, you know it fell into
the fire and the organs got, you know, got shriveled. You know,
he should have said, if you see the green spot, you know
the organs got shriveled. Since he says you know that it fell
into the fire, it sounds like if you see the green spot
even without knowing that it fell into the fire, you have to
assume by evidence of the green spot that it fell. So I
mean, you understand there's a major difference here, right? One is as
soon as you see a green spot on an organ, you've got
a problem because you have to assume it fell into the fire.
The other is the whole problem only begins when you've seen it
fall into the fire. So this last line might be a little
לאו דווקא. lav davka. He—the emphasis might be on the end, you
know, that you know that the inner organs got it. But I
think it's an interesting question, it's a very important question about whether,
you know, the green is enough to create a problem. Okay. So
let's take a look. Now to the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* continues. רבי יהושע בן לוי Levi הוה ליה ההוא תרנגולת *Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi hava lei hahu tarnegolet*. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi had
a chicken. שדריה לקמיה דרבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי *Shadreih lekameih d'Rabbi Elazar
Hakapar b'Rabbi*. He sent it to Rabbi Elazar Hakapar b'Rabbi. So here
again we have them sending it to other people. So with the
previous case, the discussion you and I had it might have been
that he was just conflicted about the הלכה *halacha*. But the other
thing that should be mentioned here is, is that טרפות *treifos* required
a lot of very practical knowledge about anatomy and various things. So
it's understandable that there were some people that were experts, so you
just send it to somebody else. Okay, so he sends it to
somebody else. I told you the story, I actually asked somebody who
knew the story better, it's probably apocryphal.
But, because we mentioned the קורקבן *korkevan*, which is the gizzard and
the whole קורקבן *korkevan*. So apparently the story was, was that, somebody
comes to a rabbi and they show him that the so the
gizzard is basically the belly button area of the chicken. So what
we call the פופיק *pupik*. Okay, so basically shows him a chicken
with, somebody brings the rabbi a chicken that there was a מחט
*machat* in the
פופיק *pupik*. So, this rabbi he
never never dealt with these things, he didn't know what it was.
So he brought it to his רעבי *rebbe*, and he said so
what's the story with this? So he
said oh he said this is the קורקבן *korkevan*, the
מחט הנמצא בקורקבן *machat hanimtza bakorkevan*, the hole in the קורקבן *korkevan*.
He says, ah, this is the הייליגע קורקבן *heilige korkevan*!
So, the rabbi said, now you can learn the whole גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* and still not know what a chicken looks like on the
inside of a chicken looks like. Okay, so anyway, so all right,
so he sent it, so this chicken was brought in front of
רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*.
So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so anyway, so ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*
had a chicken, excuse me, רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi* had a chicken, and he sent it to רבי אלעזר הקפר
ברבי *Rabbi Elazar Hakapar b'Rabbi*. So אמר ליה ירוקין הוו ואכשרי *amar
lei yarokin havhu ve-ashrei*. So he said look, they're green, and he
was kosher. What do you mean? והנן תנן *ve-ha-nan tenan*, our Mishnah
says ירוקין פסולים *yarokin pesulim*. So, that green is exactly what the
problem is. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, לא אמרו ירוקין פסולים
אלא בקורקבן ובלב ובכבד *lo ameru yarokin pesulim ela bekorkevan uvalev uvakaved*.
When it says that when the organs turn green as a result
of this fire it's פסול *pasul*, it's only about three organs: the
gizzard, the heart, and the liver. Which is quite interesting because the
liver in general is not a problem. And before we just said
the liver was only a problem when it was opposite the בני
מעיים *bnei me-ayim*. But here it's listed as those that greenness is
a problem. תניא tanya, נמי הכי *Tanya nami hachi*, we taught similarly,
באלו בני מעיים אמרו *be-eilu bnei me-ayim ameru*, which organs is turning
green a problem? בקורקבן ובלב ובכבד *bekorkevan uvalev uvakaved*, the gizzard, the
heart, and the liver. רבי יצחק בר יוסף הוה ליה ההוא תרנגולת
*Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef hava lei hahu tarnegolet*, רבי יצחק בר יוסף
*Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef* had a chicken, now presumably it doesn't even
mean his personal chicken, somebody sent it to him and he sent
it on. שדריה לקמיה דרבי אבהו *Shadreih lekameih d'Rabbi Abbahu*, he sent
it to רבי אבהו *Rabbi Abbahu*. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, and
אדומין הוו וטרפה *adumim havhu ve-terfa*. Oh, the organs were red and
he made it a טרפה treifa. *treifa*. So what do you mean?
והנן תנן אדומין כשרים *ve-ha-nan tenan adumim kesherim*, our Mishnah says that
red is the good color. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, he says
this is the flip of what we just got through saying. אדומין
שהוריקו וירוקין שהאדימו *adumim she-horiku ve-yarokin she-idimu*. If ones that are naturally
red turn green, which would be the case of the gizzard, the
heart, and the liver, that's a problem, but the same is true
in the opposite. Things which are naturally green, you must assume he
means greenish, if they turned red, then that's also a problem. So
the Mishnah is not complete. The Mishnah talks about turning green as
a result of the fire, but that's the ones that are naturally
red. If the ones that are naturally a greenish color turn red,
that's an equal problem. טרפה treifa, *treifa*, that is a טרפה treifa.
*treifa*. לא אמרו אדומין כשרים אלא בלב בקורקבן ובכבד *lo ameru adumim
kesherim ela balev bekorkevan uvakaved*. Only the heart, the gizzard, and the
liver. So again it's not exactly clear to me what it means
that the other organs are greenish. Let me see if this has
a picture. It has the heart, the liver, and the well, the
others are certainly basically more of an orangish rather than a red.
But you see what it means, here this actually is a nice
color. This is the heart, right? and this is the liver. So
those are nice red colors. And this is the gizzard, so you
see under the fat it's nice and red. Right? The intestines here
are more of a orangish and you can sort of see how
you could describe it like an orangish-greenish tint. בני מעיים *bnei me-ayim*.
Right? Yeah, so that's what he means. See, the natural red ones
if they turn green and the natural I guess he says flesh-tone
but maybe there was a greenish tint if they turned red. See,
so that here is the one of the few times where the
color really is extremely helpful. Okay, so anyway, so let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
Okay. אמר שמואל בר חייא אמר רב מני *Amar Shmuel bar Chiya
amar Rav Mani*. So אמר שמואל בר חייא *Amar Shmuel bar Chiya*
says in the name of רב מני *Rav Mani*, אדומין שהוריקו ושלוקן
וחזרו והאדימו כשרים *adumim she-horiku veshalokan vechazru ve-idimu kesherim*. If you remember
we had something like this yesterday about the shriveled up lung and
how to test if it really was a serious problem, which is
you sort of put it in lukewarm water. So here you do
the same thing. If you have things that have turned red that
should have been more of the flesh tone and you went ahead
and you cooked them, you put them in water and in boiling
water, וחזרו והאדימו *vechazru ve-idimu* and then they returned to their red
color, כשרים *kesherim*, they're kosher. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? קוטרא איי בהו
kutra ai behu because their change of color to this redness is
because they have inhaled smoke. Remember, this is a chicken that fell
into the fire. So this is what the smoke might have changed
the color, but if you do this, it basically removes those contaminants
and it gets back to its natural color. So it's not a
permanent condition. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak says, אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami sanina, once
you say you can do an experiment to see how bad the
condition is, you said that for the things that looked red, let's
try to figure out a similar experiment for the things that look
greenish that should be red. So we'll say אדומים שלא הוריקו, adumim
shelo horiku,
let's say you have—I'm sorry, no, excuse me, not that. Let's do
an experiment to see if something is a problem but it's being
masked. Let's say you have the organs that look red but and
they should be red. So maybe we should do a test, maybe
they really are sort of damaged but they're just being masked. ושלקון
והוריקו, veshalkun vehoriku, let's say you put similarly put them in boiling
water and you cooked them and then they turned this like orange-yellow,
טריפה. treifa. Let's say that now it is a טריפה. treifa. If
you're saying basically putting it in this boiling water restores it to
its natural state, so you said you had something that looked not
good, you put it in the water, it returned to its natural
color, it's okay. So let's say something looks good, you put it
in this boiling water and it turns to a bad color, so
maybe we should say the bad color is the natural state. מאי
טעמא? איגלאי בהיתייהו. igla bahita'iyu. Their shame has been revealed. So basically,
right, they have been—they were covering up their shame, something that was
being masked, and now we did this and this sort of evaporated
this false color and the true color is now revealed. So if
you can use this test to say it's kosher, let's use a
similar test to say it's טריף. treif. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav
Ashi, הלכך, hilkach, therefore, לא ליכול איניש אלא בשלקא. lo leichol inish
ela beshalka. You should not eat any chickens unless you do this
test of, you know, putting the organs in the water to see
what color they turn out. Again, what's fascinating about this גמרא Gemara.
is that we have not continued to mention the context that the
chicken fell into the fire. If you just take this statement on
face value, it means any chicken you have to first check this
inner organ. But that's not what the פוסקים Poskim say. The פוסקים
Poskim continually reassert that the context here is it fell into fire.
So even this last statement is if it fell in fire, you
would have to run a test even if everything looked okay. And
the גמרא Gemara concludes, ולא היא, velo hi, it's not true. אחזוקי
ריעותא לא מחזקינן. achzukei rei'ata la machzekinan. We do not assume problems,
ריעותא rei'ata as a problem, רע, ra, we don't make assumptions of
problems unless there's evidence that there's a problem. So if the organs
look good, we're not going to go looking for trouble. Our inspection
shows that it's okay, we're not going to do a test to
see maybe that's not true. If something looks bad, we can try
to do a test to try to prove that it's not bad.
Okay, which is again a, you know, on the one hand maybe
informed by the principle before about we don't want to waste ממונם
של ישראל, mammonam shel Yisrael, but it's also based on more formal
principles, right? About חזקות chazakas and לידת הספק leidas ha'safek in general,
which might also be, you know, a similar type of point. But
it basically means you work with the assumption that things are good,
you only stop to sort of analyze this, you know, if there's
a what we call לידת הספק, leidas ha'safek, a concrete reason to
assume it's bad. And if you then do an inspection and it
looks good, how far do you have to go, you know, is
also a question. So there are limits in terms of when are
you concerned that certain things are a problem and also how much,
you know, inspection is needed to do. So don't worry, once you've
looked and the color is good, you can stop there. Okay. Now
we have the case about what we would call the ריסוקי אברים,
risukei evarim, the being sort of blunt force and maybe the limbs
were somehow, you know, sort of—not shattered but separated or loosened, I
guess. דרסה וטרפה בכותל, darsa vetarfa bekotel, if it was trampled on
or thrown against a wall. So then you have the whole thing
about living for twenty-four hours and so on. So אמר רבי אלעזר
בן אנטיגנוס משום רבי אלעזר בר ינאי, Amar Rabbi Elazar ben Antignus
mishum Rabbi Elazar bar Yannai, הכא והכא צריכה בדיקה. achazu ve'achazu tzericha
bedika. Either way, even if it lasts for twenty-four hours, you still
have to check the inner organs. Okay, so you know, the גמרא
Gemara about this whole thing about נפולה, nefula, if you remember we
had by the cow that fell off the roof, on the one
hand it adopts certain leniencies, you only have the idea that twenty-four
hours helps mentioned by the birds, you never had it mentioned there
but we applied it there. But then you also have a pullback.
We're not going to completely say it's okay, at least you'll have
to check the inner organs even if you waited the twenty-four hours.
The גמרא however did add, if you'll remember, that if the cow
got up and walked around or the bird got up and flew
around, then you don't even have to do an internal check. Okay,
so those are the cases of נפולה. nefula. Again, it's a much
abbreviated list because, you know, we did mention the thing about the
hole in the gizzard, but there were a lot of other organs
we did not mention. But that's why we have the statement of
לוי that we generally assume that the טריפות treifos are the same.
Okay, now let's continue to the next משנה. mishna. So now we're
following the pattern. First we list what's טריף treif in the cows,
then what's kosher in the cows. Now what's טריף treif in the
birds, so the next משנה mishna what's kosher in the birds. The
אלו כשרות בעוף, Eilu k'sheiros ba-of, the following are כשר kosher in
birds. נקבה הגרגרת
או שנפסקה, Nikva ha-gargeres o she-nifseka, if there is a hole in
the trachea. Remember trachea has to be cut halfway through. Or it
is there is a crack in it like a hole running down
its length, if it doesn't go all the way to the very
top or the very bottom. היכתה חולדה על ראשה, Hikta chulda al
rosha, מקום שאינו עושה טרפה. makom she-eino osa treifa. If it was
attacked by a weasel by the head, but it was opposite a
place where there is no brains or whatever, so even if it
went all the way through, it would not have made a hole
into the membrane.
So I'm not exactly sure where that is in the head that
it's not that there's not a brain opposite, but I'm sure it's
somewhere. Okay. ניקב
הזפק. Nikav ha-zeffek. Now we said a hole in the gizzard is
a problem, a hole in the crop is not a problem. The
crop is what the food gets to before the gizzard. I don't
remember exactly how each thing functions. I'm sure somewhere they describe the
functions of them. רבי אומר אפילו ניטל, Rebbi omer afilu nital, even
if the even if the gizzard the crop is removed. Now if
you look at this picture, I don't understand how you can remove
the crop without removing the entire it's basically all connected like by
a tube. It's not like organs that like
hang and you can remove one organ. I don't get how you
would sort of remove but maybe I'm wrong, maybe this is the
tube and maybe there's like a small hole that feeds into the
tube and maybe it's possible to totally remove that. I don't know.
But anyway, I'm not exactly sure how you would do that. And
even if you would do that, wouldn't it make a hole in
the wouldn't it be considered like a hole in the esophagus or
no? Do we say that oh no, I'm sorry, by the I
keep up doing the same thing. This is the gizzard. This is
the crop. So if you see it right, it goes straight into
the crop. So I don't know how you could remove the crop
without cutting it off and presumably that would certainly be a hole
in the a hole in the esophagus.
Gizzard scroll footnote it says provided that enough of the crop remains
to enable the food to pass to the gizzard. Okay, some of
that. Thanks ר"ן Ran and באר הגולה. Beer ha-Golah.
Okay, so there, they're trying to deal with that problem. So not
fully removed, but but enough that it still passes through. Does it
say what the function of the crop is?
No,
it must grind up the both of them.
Yeah, I'm wondering if one grinds it and the other digests it
or something like that. Doesn't say.
Okay, I'm sure.
Okay, alright, so fine. So let's continue, thank you, alright, so okay,
so that is the crop, which is where it goes first. רבי
אומר אפילו ניטל, Rebbi omer afilu nital, even if it were removed.
יצאו בני מעיה ולא ניקבו. Yatzu bnei me-eha v'lo nikvu. Let's say
the organ, somehow it was cut along its belly, by presumably some
animal, and the organs of its body were falling were like out
of its body, but they had nothing had been cut. You understand
like the cavity was open, the skin was open and the organs
were hanging out, but but they there are no holes.
נשתברו גפיה, Nishtabru gapeha, if its wings were broken. נשתברו רגליה, Nishtabru
ragleha, its legs were broken. נמרטו כנפיה, Nimretu knafeha, its feathers had
been basically sort of removed, right? So that all of those it's
still כשר. kosher. רבי יהודה אומר אם ניטלה הנוצה פסולה. Rebbi Yehuda
omer im nitla ha-notza pesula. It's true if the outer feathers were
removed, the big feathers, it's okay, but the נוצה notza is basically
like the down,
the very like stuff very close, the hairy more hairy stuff, or
I don't know hairy is the word, but you know the small
stuff, not the stuff that we consider say is right closer to
the skin, which really protects it. Okay, there you have the down
of a chicken. Yeah, I mean it looks very large, very sort
of soft and it's not feather it's not what we think of
when we think of a feather, it's more right. Where's the feather?
Is this the feather over here?
Yeah, that's the feather. So the yeah, but this is right next
to the skin. So he says that that is needed to protect
the animal and if that's not on the animal, then it is
a טרפה. treifa.
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Didn't we also have like yesterday didn't we have that if the
animal was skinned it was still כשר? kosher?
By the cow. And right, that's a good point actually. That's a
nice parallel, I hadn't thought about that. And even there we so
there we said it was a טרפה, it was a debate. רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir said it was כשר kosher and the חכמים Chachamim
said it's טרפה. Now it's actually interesting because normally רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir the בר פלוגתא bar plugta of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is
רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, so it would be interesting there to think
that maybe it is parallel. Maybe the רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
כשר kosher and there if the חכמים Chachamim was רבי יהודה, Rebbi
Yehuda, then that's an exact analogy because then רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
here is saying that the down is a problem,
so maybe it is. Except here the רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is
being framed as the דעת יחיד, da'as yachid, right? The standard assumption
is not a position is not distinguishing between the down and the
other feathers. But that's a nice parallel. Okay, so תנו רבנן. Tanu
rabanan. So we taught מעשה ברבי סימאי וברבי צדוק Ma'aseh b'Rebbi Simai
u'v'Rebbi Tzadok שהלכו לעבר השנה בלוד. she-halchu l'aber ha-shana b'Lod. So these
two rabbis went to be part of a convocation at Lod. to
determine, you know, inter- the adding of a month for the year,
and so the rabbis were gathering, they had a conference in Lod,
of course because that's the airport, so that's easier to get everyone
together. All right, anyway.
Okay. ושבתו באונו. ve-shavtu be-Ono.
So on their way there, they spent the Shabbos in Ono, which
was somewhere on the way to Lod. והורו בטרפחת. ve-horu be-tarpachat. And
they gave a ruling on the tarpachat. You remember yesterday we said
the tarpachat is one of the rules words for a womb. So
a case of a womb with a hole in it or something
was brought to them and they gave a ruling on it. Now,
we have said that a missing womb is okay. So they ruled
by the womb כרבי בזפק, ke-Rebbi be-zefek, like Rebbi ruled by the
crop. What did Rebbi say by the crop? Right, Rebbi said that
even with no crop, it's kosher. So meaning they said, "Oh, the
same way Rebbi said with no crop it's kosher, we'll say with
no womb it's also kosher." There are some organs that are not
essential. So meaning that you understand why it's sort of making the
rough analogy. Okay, not again, the Gemara on the one hand says
you don't compare different treifos, but here it's saying it was the
same type of a ruling. They assumed that the womb was not
essential and they said it was kosher the same way Rebbi said
the same thing by the crop. Okay. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. So
they asked, so now we want to understand this. What I told
you was sort of the simple way of reading it, but the
Gemara has a question.
הורו בטרפחת לאיסורא Horu be-tarpachat le-issura וכרבי בזפק להתירא, ve-ke-Rebbi be-zefek le-heteira,
which is a very strange read. Did they rule that a missing
womb was assur
and actually Rashi's girsa says וכרבי בזפק להתירא. ve-ke-Rebbi be-zefek le-heteira. Maybe
they had two rulings: A, they ruled by a womb, they said
that was a treifa, and then B, there was another case about
the crop and there they ruled like Rebbi and said that it
was kosher. או דלמא, O dilma, or is this what it means:
הורו בטרפחת להתירא כרבי בזפק, Horu be-tarpachat le-heteira ke-Rebbi be-zefek, that when
they ruled by the case of the womb like Rebbi ruled by
the crop, so they ruled that a missing womb was kosher, but
we don't know really but where
was I? כרבי בזפק ke-Rebbi be-zefek אבל כרבי בזפק לא סבירא להו.
aval ke-Rebbi be-zefek lo sevira lehu. But we don't, but we don't
exactly know how they would rule by the case of the crop
itself. Meaning, is the author of this Baraita telling oh, here's an
analogy, right? The same way Rebbi says that a missing crop is
okay, they said a missing womb was okay, but maybe they themselves
don't agree with Rebbi by the crop. We don't know how they
held about that. They just said the womb was okay. The author
of the Baraita saying that's just like what Rebbi says by by
the case of the crop. So we don't know that they held
like Rebbi by the crop. So Gemara says תיקו. teiku. So that's
unresolved. So that essentially what this is trying to do is get
to the heart of excuse me, whatever prop this is, get to
the question of: Rebbi says a missing crop is okay, do we
rule like Rebbi or not? So we have this Baraita about these
two rabbis about ruling about a womb and mentioning Rebbi, but it's
a little but it's ambiguous whether it means that they they really
ruled like Rebbi by the crop.
Okay. ואמר רבה ואיתימא רבי יהושע בן לוי: Ve-amar Rabbah ve-iseima Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi: גגו של זפק נידון כוושט. Gago shel zefek nidon
ke-veshet. So we just saw there how the esophagus goes right into
the crop. So he says the the roof of the crop, you
know, basically if you were to draw like a line, you know,
you would imagine, again if you see that picture, let's get that
picture again.
Yeah, also I think this is here's some kosher. Oh, okay, that's
the page before.
No, this is a good one. Okay, so right. So here you
see, right? This is the esophagus, this is the crop, and then
it continues on to the gizzard. So we said, right? That a
hole in the crop is not a problem. But what if the
hole is right over here? Maybe that's more counted like the esophagus,
right? At what point does the esophagus end and the gizzard begin?
So it basically says if you sort of consider this as a
straight tube, a hole in this top part is essentially a hole
in the esophagus and it's a treifa. Only in the lower part
is it a hole in the crop and is it okay. Presumably
the reason why the crop is less of a problem is because
the food could pass straight through to the gizzard and still be
digested. Okay. So he says,
גגו של זפק נידון כוושט. Gago shel zefek nidon ke-veshet. The roof
of that is like the esophagus itself and a hole is a
problem. היכא? Heicha? What would be considered the roof? אמר רבי ביבי
בר אביי: Amar Rabbi Bibi bar Abaye: כל שנמתח עמו. kol she-nimtach
immo. Anything that stretches with it. So Rashi basically says it means
where this sac begins to sort of, you know, stretch into the
tube like where the walls of it begin to sort of be
stretched and pulled, that's where it's already considered to be part of
the esophagus. Okay. So that's that's okay. I mean, no, if it's
a hole is there, it's part of the esophagus and it's a
problem. Now יצאו בני מעיה, yatzu benei me'eha, if the organs have
come out of the body but there's no are not damaged, have
no hole in them. That's okay. אמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק:
Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak: לא שנו אלא שלא היפך בהן.
lo shanu ella she-lo hiphech bahen. Now all this is only if
the order of the organs has not been sort of moved around.
But if they fell out of the body and maybe you were
trying to put them back in the body, you're trying to help
the animal, and somehow you put one organ on top of the
other in the wrong way they're normally situated in the body, that's
a problem. אבל היפך בהן, aval hiphech bahen, if you you know
upturned them, טרפה. It's treifa. Now, by the way, as far as
we know, right? If the organs were slightly in the wrong position,
if everything was connected, I can't understand why that would affect the
health of an animal. Okay, anyway, but. But that's a טריפה. treifa.
דכתיב, dichtiv, the verse says, הוא עשך ויכננך, hu ascha vayechonenecha, God
has made you and established you, right, by the in דברים Devarim
there by the שירה. shira. מלמד שברא הקדוש ברוך הוא כונניות באדם,
melamed shebara Hakadosh Baruch Hu koneniyot ba'adam, God has made sort of
chambers in a person, שאם נהפך אחד מהן אינו יכול לחיות, sheim
nepach echad mehen eino yachol lychayot, that if they got everything sort
of, you know, layered, one chamber on top of the other and
things are in their right place,
and if things were situated in the wrong place you wouldn't live.
Now the purpose of this is I think to appreciate it sort
of like we say in the אשר יצר, Asher Yatzar, right, וברא
בו נקבים נקבים, uvara vo nekavim nekavim, שאם יסתם אחד מהם או
יפתח אחד מהם, sheim yisateim echad mehem o yipatei'ach echad mehem, אי
אפשר להתקיים, i efshar lehitkayeim, how like the wonder of the divine
creation that everything works so perfectly and if something was just slightly
off our bodies wouldn't work. So that's the point here, you know,
the organs are perfectly situated and if they were slightly in a
different place, you know, everything wouldn't work. But from this we learn,
we see, if the organs are in the wrong place it's not
going to work. Okay, of course you could also say by the
ברכה bracha of אשר יצר Asher Yatzar we say, what is it,
שאם יפתח אחד
מהם או שאם יסתם אחד מהם. sheim yipatei'ach echad mehem o sheim
yisateim echad mehem. Well we learned that there are some organs that
holes are a problem and there are some organs, right, so just
because you say that as a פשוט pashut doesn't mean that you
directly translate that halachically. Okay, but anyway the גמרא is translating this
halachically.
Okay, תניא, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, היה רבי מאיר אומר,
haya Rabbi Meir omer, הוא עשך ויכננך, hu ascha vayechonenecha,
God made you and established you. So a different way of translating
this word כוננך. konenacha.
רש"י Rashi says the first way was like a כן, kan, like
a base, like you established a foundation and you know things on
top of the foundation in a particular order. Okay, so now let's
hear how רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir reads this:
כאמכרכא דכולא ביה, ke'am karcha dekula bei, he made you into like
a city, a metropolis that everything is contained within you, ממנו כהנים
ממנו נביאים ממנו שריו ממנו מלכיו. mimeinu Kohanim mimeinu Nevi'im mimeinu sarav
mimeinu melachav. You don't need any of, you know, you don't need
sort of other nations. From you comes everything, כהנים, Kohanim, נביאים, Nevi'im,
prophets, you know, rulers, kings, and so on. שנאמר, shenemar, ממנו פנה
ממנו יתד, mimeinu pina mimeinu yated, you know, another פסוק pasuk that
from them comes, you know, the cornerstone and the foundation. So again
like the sense of foundation, you have everything you need to build
upon. God has given you everything that you need. But he is
talking about nationally not as a person. Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so the second explanation is God made ישראל Yisrael this specific
way, but that's not relevant to the chicken.
Right.
Exactly. Or all creatures.
Right. Exactly. Exactly. So we're choosing to look at the first דרשה,
drasha, not the second, and to translate it very halachically. You're right,
but I like the contrast. Israel, chickens. That's true. Okay, let me
just read this one last story. ההוא ארמאה, hahu Armaa, there was
a certain non-Jew. It's actually quite interesting why the גמרא sometimes calls
non-Jews ארמאה, Armaa, this is not actually a censored word as עכו"ם
Akum is, and I don't know how many Armenians were in בבל.
Bavel. But anyway, there was an Armenian or a non-Jew דחזייה להו
גברא דנפל מאיגרא לארעא. dechazyei lehu gavra denafal me'igra le'ara. He saw
somebody that fell off of a roof to the ground. פקעי כרסיה,
pakei karshei, and his stomach burst open, ונפק מעייניה, venafak ma'ayanay, and
his organs, his like inner organs came out of his stomach. But
they were still attached, you know, nothing had broken in terms of
the inner organs. אייתי ליה לבריה, aytei livrei, he brought over his
son, of the person who fell, ושחטיה קמיה, veshachatei kamei, and he
made it look like, this is not literal, like he was killing
his son. He did this to cause the person to faint so
he could operate on him. Okay, so he made it look like
he was killing this injured person's son באחיזת עיניים, beachizat einayim, with
like
an illusion. Okay, he did it, he made it appear that way.
אינגיד, ingid, so the person who had fallen on the ground, he
had already suffered a pretty serious trauma, so he sort of swooned
and ואיתנח ve'itnach and he fainted and ועול מעייניה, ve'ul ma'ayanay, so
what happened was apparently so he then put the organs inside this
person,
now, and therefore וחייטיה לכרסיה, vechaytei lekarshei, he sewed up his stomach.
So you see that even by people, even if the organs come
out, you can put them back in and therefore you can, right,
save the person. Okay, now you had one last question Charlie? Right.
Well,
I should just say one last thing is that רש"י Rashi makes
it sound...